<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Newgate,] Octob. 30. 1693. Whereas it was witnessed against Shadrach Cooke on Tuesday the 17th. of this present month, at the Old Bailey, that he did forge a pasport to France in my Lord Nottingham's name  ...</title>
            <author>Cooke, Shadrach, 1655?-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6038A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895627</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895627</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2350:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Newgate,] Octob. 30. 1693. Whereas it was witnessed against Shadrach Cooke on Tuesday the 17th. of this present month, at the Old Bailey, that he did forge a pasport to France in my Lord Nottingham's name  ...</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Shadrach, 1655?-1724?</author>
                  <author>Taylor, Ralph, 1648 or 9-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption title and opening words of text.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Page [1] contains a statement of innocence signed "Sha. Cooke"; page [2] has a declaration signed "Ralph Taylor", supporting Cooke and verifying Cooke's statements at his trial. Taylor's text begins "Many having been led into a mistake by, and some still cavelling and disputing upon, these words, ...".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Forgery) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:153140:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="document">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Octob. 30. 1693.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WHEREAS it was witneſſed againſt <hi>Shadrach Cooke</hi> on Tueſday the 17<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of this preſent Month, at the <hi>Old Bailey,</hi> That he did forge a Paſport to <hi>France</hi> in my Lord <hi>Nottingham</hi>'s Name.</p>
                        <p>I <hi>Shadrach Cooke,</hi> Prieſt of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> having utterly diſown'd the Fact at the Time and Place aforeſaid, do here Again, upon the Receiving the Bleſſed Sacrament of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Body and Blood, and as I hope for any Benefits by my Saviour's Death and Sufferings, ſolemnly declare that I am altogether lgnorant and Innocent of this Matter, and that I know nothing directly or indirectly relating thereunto, either as to my ſelf, or any other; and that I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of any thing in any ſort or kind, nor ever was concerning the Counterfeiting my Lord <hi>Nottingham</hi>'s Hand or Seal. This I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare upon the ſincere Faith of a Chriſtian, without any reſerve, in the full and due Senſe of theſe Words, or any other, that can expreſs or ſignify an undiſguiſed intire Innocence in this Caſe.</p>
                        <p>I do here alſo declare, That I do from the very bottom of my Heart, as becometh a Chriſtian in this moſt holy Duty, forgive ſuch that raiſed this great Scandal of me, or that occaſioned my Suffering upon it.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>SHA. COOKE.</hi> Declared in the preſence of us who did Communicate with him.
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ralph Taylor,</hi> D. D.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Simon Lowth,</hi> D. D.</item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>William Carr.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Rich. Hughes.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:153140:2"/>
            <p> MAny having been led into a Miſtake by, and ſome ſtill cavelling and diſputing upon, theſe Words, [<hi>Mr.</hi> Cooke <hi>ſaid that what he did was out of a Principle of Conſcience</hi>] publiſhed in a Paper entituled, <hi>The Proceedings, &amp;c.</hi> printed for <hi>Ric. Baldwin</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> As if Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> had really own'd, and juſtify'd the Fact charg'd upon him by pleading Conſcience for it.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Ralph Taylor,</hi> D. D. out of a due regard to Truth and Peace, and out of a ſincere deſire to ſatisfie all unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic'd Enquirers after the ſame in this particular, do declare, That being preſent at the <hi>Old Bailey</hi> on the 17<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of this Month, when Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> was call'd to anſwer what was laid to his Charge, I did then obſerve the ſaid Mr. <hi>Cooke</hi> moſt vehemently to deny,<note n="*" place="margin">May all the Judgments and Puniſhments, that God has in Store for Sinners, light upon my head, if I am not altogether Ignorant of what I am charg'd with, in Thought, Word and Deed.</note> even with an Impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <note place="margin">The Imprecation.</note> what was teſtify'd againſt him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Counterfeiting my Lord <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi>'s Hand and Seal; and did hear him very Solemnly and Zealouſly aſſert his Innocence, as near as I can remember, in theſe Words; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon my Salvation I did not do it: As I hope for Mercy in Heaven I ſeal'd no ſuch Paper: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Word of a Prieſt I did no ſuch thing.</hi> And what he ſaid <hi>of Conſcience</hi> was before he ſpoke to the Fact wherewithal he was charg'd, and had reference not to what was teſtify'd or done concerning that particular Fact, but to what he himſelf had omitted, and not done, during the long time of his being in Cuſtody, as the means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing his Liberty: Nor was there any thing then ſaid, that I could perceive by Mr. <hi>Cooke,</hi> that might give the leaſt colour or occaſion, to any there preſent, who heard and obſerv'd him, to apprehend that he own'd the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting of my Lord <hi>Nottingham</hi>'s Hand and Seal, or that he ſhould ſay, That he did it out of a Principle of Conſcience.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ralph Taylor.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 25. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
